this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco slash SE radio hello they
see Sonya cross Lee for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Simon Riggs about advanced features
of the Postgres database simon is a
professional developer and consultant
with lots of experience with a variety
of database technologies he's a regular
conference speaker on database
technologies and I first met him several
years ago a post-grad user group meeting
where he's presenting some of the
clustering and replication features
that's committed to the Postgres
database Sam has continued to contribute
major features to Postgres and a CTO of
second quadrant consultancy has built a
team of developers and consultants
delivering advanced Postgres
implementations to enterprise clients I
hope that introduction does you justice
Simon our welcome to software
engineering radio thank you very much
Postgres is widely promoted as the
world's most advanced open-source
database and today I'd like to talk in
detail about some of those advanced
features and but first could you please
summarize the ways in which you think
Postgres is more advanced than other
databases sure well I think the the
first and foremost feature is that it
follows the SQL
standard extremely closely now that may
not seem like the most advanced thing
but that the standard is is long and
complex it takes a lot of work to to get
us to to match that closely but in
general Postgres has got broad and very
deep features support across a whole
range of different use cases and it's my
view that post-crisis is more than just
a relational database and I'd like to
explain that to you if if we go in that
direction a couple of other things I'd
like to mention as to why were the most
advanced the query planner and in
general performance is very advanced in
Postgres for example there are six
different types of index available with
post cards many more than most other
databases and Postgres also invented the
partial index and expression indexes
both of which are very useful for
performance Postgres is also very
extensible we've pretty much invented
that thought and that brings in a whole
sort of vast array of add-ons that you
can get with post-credits that you know
other people need to add themselves to
the core engine whereas Postgres can
just expose an interface to allow people
to add their own things okay but the
last one is actually ease of use which
is a strange one because you know some
people would say in the past it was hard
to install and that kind of thing but
the main thing with postcodes really is
it just works and we designed things in
a way that causes the least surprise for
developers and we also go to a lot of
trouble to ensure its robust and
accurate for example a couple of years
ago we discovered that there'd been some
minor minor error in the accuracy of one
of the functions and I think there was
sort of 10 decimal places into the
results there was some weird error and
we spent a lot of time fixing that now
that kind of attention to detail is what
makes
squares the most advanced because it
takes time and it takes love and care
really to to make the feature set full
and complete yeah that's definitely
something we can appreciate and then and
I know that you personally spend a lot
of time doing that one and the team of
people and a thanks for that excellent
list I think you know with that give us
a a good structure for our conversation
so let's start at the top and let's
return to some of the features of the of
the SQL standard which you said Postgres
has good support for yeah I think most
of our listeners will be familiar with
the Select Select statement and but
there are lots of more advanced features
SQL that maybe they they're not that
familiar with what are the things that
Postgres supports that developers might
be unfamiliar with what could be useful
for them in their in their work yeah so
there's there's some interesting
additions to the SQL language that
people are just simply not familiar with
obviously people have heard of things
like joins and sub selects between
tables yeah but we've extended the
insert command which allows you to
implement something that does what's
known as an up cert in that it will
attempt to do an insert but if the rows
already there it will turn it into an
update so that's one of the first things
so instead of getting an unhelpful
conflict error your statement will just
work it will just work and what's more
important there is that we spend quite a
lot of time designing in a way that
means that it will keep you all there's
guaranteed to give you an answer it
doesn't just sort of world around
forever and without deciding what to do
so it's quite a subtle implementation
and it took actually multiple years to
to get that to work so that was time
well spent
because it saves time for the user
uh-huh okay excellent so moving on from
there my next point of colle I think
would be window functions which is
something that frankly many people have
never even heard of yeah but but a
window function is is something that
allows you to look at the results of a
query in in an ordered way for example
if you're looking at a time series and
you want to look at the last three
points on the time series then you need
a window function now a lot of people
think that that's not possible in SQL
and it wasn't in the early versions of
SQL it was quite a simple language and
SQL did more than 20 years ago receive
criticism for some of the things it
lacked what people don't realize is that
those things were added to the SQL
standard and Postgres has supported them
for many years so for example if you
want to look at a time series you want
to calculate a moving average over data
if you want to look at a lag these are
all things that can be done in the SQL
language and done not just you know we
can barely touch them I'm talking about
implementing fully with with decent
optimization though so it's been been
implemented for more than ten years and
it's been highly optimized so you know
that that's that's the first thing and
what are the keywords that you would use
to structure a window function in your
SQL statement so there's an over clause
which allows you to calculate aggregates
across a window clause and then you can
structure things so that you can say
what type of window it's going to be
whether it's a moving window or whether
it's a window that goes back to the
beginning of the series
so you might have a cumulative total
alongside the total for example so you
can list out a range of numbers with it
with a cumulative total alongside them
or you could smooth out your data across
a number of different points as I said
to calculate moving averages and that
kind of thing so there's a lot of
complex statistical funk
built into Postgres and and that is one
of the the ways that we wish support
them and so in your example of the time
series and choosing the last three
points yes if if my
timestamp column was the series that I'm
interested in then I would I would
remote window over the times timestamp
column and then perform some statistics
or other calculations on the on the
resulting sets yes so the the results
there are actually called window
aggregate functions and so you would for
each row in the table you would access
the sliding window and then you to
calculate the results of the outgo go
across the sliding window okay sir
yeah and deftly please don't ask me what
the syntax is because I have to look in
the manual as well right that's not the
point is it it's whether it fully
supports the standard and does so in a
in a useful and performant way and I
think that importantly as well it's the
you know is the code that a developer
would have to write client-side in order
to do that work and to do that work in a
way that's performant I know it works
over large data sets it's you know the
Postgres it has that has that power
right yeah very much so yeah yeah
another example of how we handle that is
visitor there's a thing called a with
clause that allows you to define out
what's called a common table expression
so that allows you to define a fragment
of code that could be reused many times
within your SQL obviously that kind of
thing makes it much more sensible to
write correct code because if you have
to have sections of code that are
similar you know then that avoids
mistakes but the the interesting thing
about the with sub-command is that we
support the with recursive form which is
actually in the SQL standard and what
that allows you to do is to search
a network or a hierarchy and quite
surprising to many people is the fact
that it allows you to write graph
queries inside Postgres and most people
believe that's not possible in yet it is
actually completely possible and not
just possible very well performance in
that it's been fully optimized as well
so there's some some really impressive
features in there that that I used in
production and in many many parts of the
world so how would I need to structure
my data in order to be able to run a
graph query recursively over that well
the main thing it that's needed is
connections between the data elements we
don't impose a fixed structure on your
data before you can use a graph query
which some other approaches do require
you to have a sort of strict structuring
so if you have the the old example from
years ago was the the employee table
where employees have managers and their
managers can have managers and you and
you can write a recursive query that
sort of says you know what's the the
total salary of all the people in the in
my department for example and you would
start with you go out from there and in
a graph moving from employee to employee
and it isn't something where you for
each link you need to write an extra
join you can actually do that
recursively so it doesn't matter how
deep the hierarchical Network is you can
still search it so we're not limiting
you to a particular sort of property
graph model or something like that you
you can use any sort of data so it could
be XML data or JSON data that's there
and you're following links between data
items so and all of that would be fully
supported okay and the common table
expression is when you when you say it's
a it's a width Clause yes I'm thinking
that it's a definition of the view
within within your statement is that is
that the right way of thinking about
those oh yeah especially when you're
doing the sort of with clause is just
sort of a fragment of code that would be
reused but the wither recursive you have
a starting point for the query and then
an iterator that moves you to the next
data item again these are very advanced
features of SQL that most people don't
know about and post-credits fully
supports so yeah excellent
maybe maybe now's a good time to move on
to the broad and deep feature support
because you specifically mentioned there
that it's not just asked you out yes in
the database and that sounds something
interesting that we should explore so
was what's happened over the years is
that post grows because it's extensible
it's actually been used as as a platform
for development of of wider features for
example GIS features were added by the
post GIS project and that's all been
done by using the extensibility features
user-defined functions user-defined data
types first types of indexing that have
been added and as a result the the post
GIS package implements the the full GIS
standard for use within post grows so
postcodes when you plug that in becomes
a GIS database as well but there's there
a similar sort of use case packages in
full text support of a document support
and where we're also now realizing that
postcodes actually already has graph
support and we're adding time series
capabilities as well by the the fairly
recent partitioning support that's been
added so the the functionality really
doesn't just go in one particular
direction it covers a whole range of use
cases and that was what makes it a very
useful general-purpose database because
if you've got a database and it has a
little bit of graph a little bit of GIS
some text some Nall relational features
it can accommodate all of that all at
once in the one application without you
needing to resort to sort of
microservice architecture
so what kind of features what kind of
functions could I perform with a GIS
database I mean it's really to do with
viewing maps and map data so the year
the post GIS package Maps the world as
if it was coated onto just a flat
surface and then you can look at things
in terms of sort of bounding boxes and
lines between nodes and things like that
so it's actually extremely complex the
support is it goes well beyond what your
average database person would imagine
and it's actually a relative world
contender now it's used for extremely
complex GIS applications basically as a
whole industry out there of of people
looking at geography factors and they
store everything in in posterior so it's
got a a wide domain and then very often
there's not much crossover and and can I
build indexes using geometric features
and make that performance yeah that's
one of the the great things here
actually this there's multiple types of
index that you can build for that
service the equivalent of our tree
support which is pretty useful and then
there's a KD tree that we can use so the
there's actually multiple styles of
index which have different properties
depending on what types of things that
you're looking to optimize whether
you're trying to optimize search time or
whether you're trying to minimize the
size of the index or optimize for
maintenance of the index for example
these are all things that you can sort
of select your choice of index type
depending on your use case sorry it's so
complex right yes that's the that's the
thing I'm trying to get across really so
and that's all kind of through the post
GIS extension that's how those those
features that added into the database
and a similar set of features for for
temporal data
and for the other other additional types
yeah so we did actually have the text
full text stuff as an external package
but some years ago that was brought
directly inside the server core so we
now have got full text support actually
in the server core but the the indexing
that I was describing there the index
types a part of the core server but some
of the implementation exists in in the
external packages so for example they'll
be a an external package that implements
a particular datatype and then searches
on that datatype would be it would use
the internal index mechanisms but yeah I
mean basically it's um it's not just one
databases many databases because you can
build the the types of support you need
in and to give yourself a kind of
integrated platform so I really think of
it more as less of a database and more
of a more of a data platform okay and
the full text support is that will that
cope with free text unstructured text
yes very much so we've got a stemmer
package built into the core there's
quite advanced full-text support you can
set up dictionaries and stop word lists
and there's this quite an extensive
range of features there it's by no means
a a trivial sort of box tic feature is
you know it's the full deal really and
and does that have a query interface
that just slots into SQL is there
anything special keywords that I need to
have access to well a lot of it is done
via functions the the actual
configuration of it allows you to set up
parses and dictionaries and you can have
you know dictionaries in different
languages and that kind of thing so it's
actually a fallen complex support which
also supports collations and that kind
of thing so yeah it's not something that
I want to delve into in in massive
detail on a call I mean I could
I'll call just on that topic but it's
good and these extensions that you're
talking about are these these are
different from the foreign data wrappers
yes so the the front data wrappers is an
API that allows us to to write access
packages to other databases so for
example is packages written that will
allow you to access my sequel or Oracle
or you know very sort of generic JDBC
data sources and that will what you do
there is you set up a thing called a
foreign table which is essentially a a
stub we access the stub the SQL then
gets passed through to the remote server
you will execute a query and then bring
data back to us so that that really
allows post queries then to big comer I
can add o to HAARP across all the
different database types and I know that
that's quite popular with MongoDB who
use the the Postgres technology to to
give you access to their own data stops
that's really interesting use their
words data platform data hook you know
it's really extending the concepts of a
database well I think that's really the
where we're going because you know the
time was when you put stuff in a
database it just kind of sat there until
you got it back out again now there's
much greater requirement for it to do
something useful in the age of business
intelligence you know we need more from
our from our data than just simply a
storage mechanism obviously you know you
need to depend upon those basics of
storage and and you know high
availability and backup and that kind of
thing but but working beyond that it has
to provide a wider range of
functionality to to fit in the modern
enterprise there's there's too much
going on
to just store it and then bring it back
again misty you know it's not enough
just to do that anymore okay so you you
have features that you can help process
the data as well you mentioned you know
the query planner yes as being advanced
you know if you're handling all of these
different types of data I can imagine
you're gonna you're putting some real
heavy loads on on the query planner
being able to optimize queries it in all
these different scenarios yeah I mean
that's that's interesting point you
might imagine that some of these things
aren't fully or properly optimized well
what we've also done as well as extend
the database so you can add user-defined
data types
but with those users to find data types
you can also add into the database
statistics collection routines that are
appropriate to those data types and so
as a result you can write a a query that
says you know give you know give me all
the data in that bounding box and it's
it's all fully optimized and you know
what we've done is to Civics extend the
statistic system and the optimizer to
cope with it okay so as well as as well
as extending that the types of data you
extend the query planner and the
optimizer to be able to to handle them
as well yes yes by spy by extending the
support for for new types of statistical
data about those data types that's
that's really interesting and you've
also talked about different indexes in
hey so you mentioned a couple of indexes
for for the GIS data types is there
particular types of indexes that
developers might not be aware of to
using Postgres definitely so the the
basic in
type that everybody will be familiar
with his the-- is the tree or b tree
index type then people might also have
heard of hash index which allows you to
go straight to the data without sort of
navigating the full tree we've also
extended that so if you've got data that
is located by date or by number you can
use something called a block range index
which is a very small index type so it's
designed for very large data we also
support an inverted index called the GN
index and there's another two indexed
types called a gist and an SP gist and
these the G in in all three of those
last index types mentioned is stands for
generalized and there's been a lot of
research in the last 10 or 20 years
about generalized search trees or
generalized indexing mechanisms and some
of this research to create these
concepts was actually sponsored by the
US government and that work has been
taken and put into Postgres so as a
result of that we now support not just
different types of index boat
index mechanisms that can be further
extended themselves and that allows you
to support multiple different kinds of
structuring with an end in with in an
index that allows it to work efficiently
in in different ways gosh I'm not even
going to try to explain some of those
things on a call but you know the main
thing is it gives you options and you
can use those options to some good
decisions about how to index different
types of data what would be a good use
case then for for one of these
generalized index types
okay so post Crozier was actually the
first database to implement something
called nearest-neighbor indexing so if
you for example
holding your mobile phone and you want
to press it and say show me the nearest
coffee shop you might think that that is
a is kind of an easy type of query but
it turns out it's not because you need a
specialized index type that will cope
with the the fact that you're actually
looking at things near you
not you know rather than in a specific
place and Postgres was the first
database to implement that type of query
via an index previous to that people
used what's called bounding box
techniques and they were at least 10
times slower so so Postgres implemented
that using an index it's called
nearest-neighbor
indexing ok and and is that a
calculation between two points exactly
yeah
so it sounds quite complex but you know
the if I showed you the query of it
you'd go okay yeah that's pretty easy to
write so basically we just have you know
a column of that says location we put
the specialized kind of index on it and
then we just use a particular form of
where clause to retrieve the rows from
it and it works using an index rather
than doing some kind of full day to scan
okay that's interesting so is that you
you're indexing with an expression yes
that's great so you can look it up
basically it's kinda a sniper KNN
indexing allows you to look at the data
points that the nearest to you and then
obviously you you know you could put an
extra filter of coffee shop on that in
order to just put things out and make
that into the the search that I
described no that's that's good and are
there other uses of expressions within
indexes yeah I mean we support
expression indexes as well so you can
build an index ons
you know the first 10 characters of a
field site or you can you know index
well any
expression that you can execute so any
function that would retrieve a result
from a column can be indexed so it's
quite advanced functionality I will so
support partial indexing which means you
can index all of the rows that are null
for example rather than having to index
all of the rows in the table so that so
that can save save space and improve
search performance absolutely yep
exactly those two things happen
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software the customers love
digitalocean stands out from the crowd
due to its simplicity high performance
and no billing surprises join a
community of over 3.5 million developers
on digital ocean sign up with a free
$100 infrastructure credit at doco / SC
radio it obviously indexes a you know
cool to making it database performance
is there anything else that we should
cover with indexes do you think well I
mean this there's many other good
features but I think someone long-term
guyot one of the other vendors was asked
a question on his retirement whoa if
he'd have if he could go back and spend
more time on what would he spend time on
and he just replied indexes right now as
a result that makes me think we've done
the right thing by having that that
easily the the widest and most complex
serve index types of any any database
even even baiting commercial and and
that's you know referring back to this
concept of these generalized indexes
yeah and their extensibility exactly yet
we keep coming back to extensibility and
its really does seem you know the
Postgres Postgres core functions have
been built from
extensions over the years pulling
functionality in there it's a other
particular extensions that are
interesting and relevant at the moment
well I mean these there's actually what
this creates is actually an ecosystem of
tools for people that want to build
additional functionality in the system
but they don't want to spend the time to
bring it into the core server I mean we
release on what was once regarded as
quite an aggressive time scale of of
annual releases but in in terms of if
you're trying to build an application
you can't submit something to post grows
then just wait for the next release
because that's basically 12 to 18 months
so if you want new functionality now on
your system you can build an extension
and you can get it within one to three
months you can have that functionality
built into your to your database so it's
it's a way of expanding the
functionality of the data platform but
it's also a way of delivering that
functionality in useable form for
applications so delivering it quickly as
well but as I said what that's done is
it's created a whole ecosystem of
hundreds of small tools and utilities
and plugins all of which together make
Postgres into a whole range of power a
sort of powerful different things so
it's not one thing it's anything you
want it to be ok if these extensions
difficult to write a very complicated
interfaces that I need to understand to
write one well postcode supports quite a
range of internal IP eyes that you can
have access to a lot of the extensions
out there are open source and so you can
copy an existing one so really what you
need to work out is which api's should
you be using to provide this additional
functionality and you know how am I
going to go about using that obviously
if you're building an extension that you
expect thousands or millions of people
to use
you need to go to a lot more care in in
the development of it than you would do
on a sort of single function just for
your usage but so there's a whole range
of sort of emulation functions and
monitoring facilities for example second
quadrant publishes the the multi master
extension PDR for bi-directional
replication and that is available now as
as just an extension to the database so
it just plugs straight in and away you
go
okay so that's yeah that's obviously it
an advanced feature data replication
going beyond just a handling different
types
Postgres performs that that job very
well maybe just describe the concepts
behind the replication yeah sure so so
we support a couple of different kinds
of replication the first kind is
physical replication where we actually
take a copy of the transaction log and
we send that to another location and by
by doing so we're able to offer high
availability so if you stream there in
real time to another server then you can
have the choice of sending that
asynchronously meaning you commit your
transaction and then you send the data
somewhere else or you can do it
synchronously where the the commit
whites in a queue until your data has
been sent to a secondary server and then
it returns so you get your choice of
whether you want to add latency to give
you protection guarantees or whether you
want speed in in that the commit will
come back to you quickly but you don't
yet know whether your data is safe and
Postgres actually does that in quite a
clever way and that we allow you to make
that choice at the individual
transaction level so you can have some
transactions that you consider important
ones being committed synchronously and
slightly less important ones you can
have executing much faster
asynchronously so that's the
the physical replication what we then do
is when we ship the data to a secondary
server we run that server as what's
called a hot standby server and you can
actually execute queries on the standby
nodes and what you can do there is you
can add as many standby nodes as you
want to give you a full server farm
where you're able to execute thousands
and thousands of queries across the many
different servers so so that allows you
to to effectively have an extensible
cache built of additional servers we
also supports cascading replication
which allows you to have those servers
connect together so you can actually
have a hierarchy of standby service so
to give you a full server farm what we
also have is something that we've
introduced in the last couple of years
is called a logical replication and this
is where we only send the data changes
not the whole transaction log so the
first reason is that that saves
bandwidth when you're sending it across
region but the other thing is that the
the logical replication is much more
flexible and we can actually use it as
some kind of real-time data pump to
other applications in the enterprise and
most importantly we can send it to other
versions of Postgres so as a result of
this functionality we're able to a full
online upgrade so a near zero time
upgrade zero downtime upgrade of your
servers and obviously that's what people
are looking for now is to never take
their systems down ok so that you can
maintain availability because it's it's
it's a logical replication yes you can
only physically replicate the
transaction log between identical
versions of Postgres that's correct yes
so even though it's quite an efficient
replication mechanism it's not one that
works cross version and so if you
want to publish data across to a remote
site you really would prefer the the
logical replication mechanism buddies
but he's because of its ability to go
cross version it allows you to
continuously upgrade every time there's
a new major version come comes out you
can upgrade fairly soon to that you have
to wait three years for the for the next
sort of window of opportunity which is
what used to happen in the old days if I
want to build a higher variability
system with a with a large amount of
data in it you know what what kind of
orders of magnitude of numbers in terms
of database size and bandwidth what am I
kind of looking up for the capabilities
I need from my hardware well I mean
things are very efficient now so while I
would not like to sort of throw throw
too many numbers at you I can tell you
some some sizes of things but it really
does depend upon the hardware that you
spend your money on us to you know to
what kind of performance you're getting
out of this but there are post-credits
database is out there that are above 50
terabytes on a single node and you know
it's very frequent to see databases
above 10 terabytes or above a terabyte
so I would have said that most of the
customers that I deal with personally
our systems above terabytes in size and
they have extremely high transaction
rates I think that's the the other thing
has changed in in recent years is it
isn't uncommon to see transaction rates
of more than a thousand transactions a
second and in some cases you'll see
above ten thousand or or or more and you
know in in many cases so it's you know
the amount of data flying around now is
is really quite extreme and it's
difficult to get your head around the
differences between sort of low low end
transaction rate systems and the very
highest transaction rates
there are people out there they're
really pushing the barriers back of of
what's possible is that where you would
need the farmer service he in order to
really to get the optimum use from from
Postgres in those scenarios did we look
at paralyzing queries and things like
that to get us to run yeah so so
parallel query currently with with core
Postgres operates only on a single node
so if you've got sort of four or eight
CPU systems then you can get some decent
parallelism going on those single nodes
in terms of postcodes operating across
multiple servers you'd need to be
looking at something like postcodes
excel before you could or prey across
multiple nodes so it's it's a few years
yet before core postcodes itself will
will provide that functionality but
again this you know there's there's
different versions of postcards and
different packages that you can get that
enable that type of functionality okay
interesting and is that replication
something that's being actively
developed at the moment other other
changes in future releases yeah I mean
we've we've just made a lot of changes
in Postgres 12 that relate to how the
configuration works and there's been
pretty continuous change in the
replication functionality over the years
I mean the streaming replication feature
went in in 2010 and then there was a
sort of big surge of work after that but
actually the amount of changes stayed
fairly constant is what I think is
surprising is that or maybe it's not
surprising but because people are using
it heavily in production they've got
lots of small requirements for
performance changes and things like that
so I for example I about 18 months ago I
spent a lot of time myself working on
replication latency and we
removed sort of various bottlenecks that
were occurring there each of those
things takes quite a lot of work but um
you know obviously it's where you might
call polishing work rather than you know
initial feature development but it can
still be very complex so there's a yeah
there's lots of things still going into
postcodes it really yeah I think that's
the surprising thing when you when you
call it the most advanced relational
most uh most advanced database you would
think that we would be feature complete
but it's actually the opposite way
around the more users we have the more
demand there is for new features right
your work will never finish yeah it
looks that way yeah thankfully and we we
talked about some very advanced use
cases there some very high volumes
higher transaction rates but back at the
beginning you mentioned you know that
Postgres ease is easy to use yes install
on use so is that is that a journey from
your from your first install to you know
the multi node server farm can you talk
us through what that journey might look
like and steps on the way well I think
you know especially with the replication
stuff I know that people go will say
over applications really complex but
believe me we've simplified it a lot
from the way other vendors have
implemented it so for example in order
to make your application synchronous you
only have to touch one parameter to
change that and the number of
application parameters overall is
relatively relatively small so you know
what you need to do to to get the
service to work together is you just set
up a node with the software on it and
then you can launch what's called a base
backup to copy the initial server yeah
and then you then you start it up and it
will begin talking to the master node
and it will bring across all of the
changes and it will just
continued to work so these things you
know I mean now obviously we have made
even simpler over the years but in
essence we designed it from the from the
very first guy that it was going to be
as simple to use as possible and with
very few parameters and commands and I
think we you know we have achieved that
obviously as more people add complexity
that parameters emerge but in order to
build up a whole server farm you
basically just point the standby nodes
at the master and then begin flowing the
data across and these days that is just
a single command in order to get it to
to begin that the the the backup and
begin the sending of the transaction log
okay and if I had you know a 10 terabyte
database or something and I wanted to
replicate that you know that's obviously
gonna take some time even with a very
high bandwidth connection now what's up
monitoring would I what I need to have
in place would how would I know that I
was caught up and in sync on ago was
ever falling behind yes so I think
that's one of the things that's taken
longest to to build in is actually the
decent monitoring facilities but we do
have the capability now time to manage
and monitor the the replication lag we
can measure that error as a as an amount
of time or as an amount of bytes we
don't actually yet have something that
predicts how long it will take to do the
the full backup and start but that is
something that I actually wrote the spec
for just to die in fact so that I never
believe a progress bar anyway yes let me
know you know I mean that's the that's
the funny thing I mean obviously was
we're sitting here discussing it you
know everybody's got the same feeling
about progress bars and not not trusting
them and that's why you know we we
wanted to you know if we do this we have
to like you know do it properly we
and just have something that kind of
kind of sort of works when you squint
okay and is there anything else that you
wanted to include in it so either ease
of use well you know I think robustness
is ease of use you know if something
breaks all the time or just gives you
strange messages then that's very
frustrating so so robustness is and
dependability means that you can hit
your deadlines you can trust the
software accuracy means that you know
you can always trust that we've done the
right thing we haven't truncated your
data reserve set it snarling weird
circumstances or something like that and
when you when you go to use a feature
you can also trust that it's been
implemented and in complete form and and
as a result of that you can actually use
it you know with it with a good level of
trust security these days is also a big
feature but I'd really call that an ease
of use feature because if something
doesn't have security then you know then
you have to go to some level of
difficulty to isolate it so that it can
stop it from being attacked worse with
post grades you know you've got that
level of trust there that we've you know
we've done a lot for you in terms of
security and what kind of features would
you include in security yeah so I mean
we've you know we've recently updated
the authentication technology to to 256
bit encryption that's pretty advanced
that's called scram and it uses a
underlying API called sazzle so what
we've done there is we've we've
implemented the very latest technology
but also implemented it using the API
that will allow us to to keep up to date
as much as possible with that technology
as it evolves okay and so that's better
authenticated access to to the database
is that right yeah that's right we we
also implement something called host
based authentication
which is basically allows you to
whitelist or blacklist different
addresses or IP ranges and that kind of
thing so it really allows you to control
the level of security that you've you've
got in the system and if somebody for
example Act tries to access the system
with a user ID that doesn't exist we
don't reply with things like user ID
does not exist because obviously that's
you know information to the to the
person trying to to hack the system so
we go to a lot of trouble to to make
that look like it's a valid user but you
just didn't know the password for
example so okay yeah that makes complete
sense good and is there anything else
that you would particularly like to
mention we've covered a lot in this
conversation I'm sure there's a lot more
yeah well I think the you know there's a
couple of things out there we've got
very well thought-out support for for
time zones good internationalization
support and we also support something
called serialization which is a mode
that allows you to trust that the the
data in the database makes makes a lot
of sense what's called transaction
isolation there are various access
problems that people are simply unaware
of that databases go to a lot of trouble
to to get right and if you just access a
data store that's got no you know
thought given to to the transaction
isolation modes then it does make it
harder to use because you get strange
problems with you know numbers that
don't add up and you know data that
appears to have disappeared and phantom
reads and that kind of thing that's good
there's some strange anomalies so these
these would be when there are concurrent
modifications being made to the database
exactly so yeah that the basic physics
of it because if you've got you know
data's in two places if you look at the
the first data location and read what it
says and then you come back
then you go to the second data location
well obviously during that pause the
first data location can have changed and
you can get into a sort of strange
situation where you if you try and add
up the values in two separate locations
you can end up with a value that never
existed in the database at the same time
for example because you're looking at
one and then you're looking at another
yeah and so there's quite a lot of
support in the database for levels of
care with that so obviously if we're
handling money for example you don't
really want to be lucky your bank
accounts and have them not add up for
example right so that's a pretty serious
situation and that's if you access data
in a pretty simple data store then you
don't get that level of coverage and you
don't get that level of protection so we
go to a lot of trouble to explain the
types of sort of physics data anomaly
that can exist and what you should do
about it and when when we were talking
about replication the you could control
how the data was replicated at the
transaction level and other other
controls in place for different
transaction isolation levels yeah I mean
we're so within the database you can
specify the the type of transaction
isolation level you wanted at the
transaction level so you can specify for
the whole database if you want but you
can actually request different levels
depending on the type of data
manipulation that you're planning
obviously making that work across nodes
is significantly harder and that is
something that we're working on right
now but you know it's obviously a an
important thing for the future the only
problem is that physics is against us
there because there's various theorems
that say that you can't you can't have
it both consistently and quickly yes
and yeah I've always thought of Postgres
as being the database that would provide
you with the consistent answer in the
accurate answer yeah and is that right
or is that again something that's
tunable well it's that that is our hope
by default that was
always the default we would pick but we
recognize there are times when you
really do need to go faster and you
might be able to prove that your
transactions are in fact correct for
some reason and so you're happy to turn
things to a to you know sort of
potentially less safe option for me I
think it's important to have that user
control of performance v robustness and
consistency I think that's quite an
important lever to say look I need it
quick damn it as against look I really I
need it as slow as it gets it's just got
to be correct yeah yeah and and a whole
range of options in between and now I
mean you know managers can be sometimes
you know say now that I want it you know
tomorrow and 100% correct and you know
it's like well I have both right so but
you know so that's why we want to give
people a whole range of different
choices for their performance and
robustness and that's the direction that
we've been taking postcodes in is to is
to give you the robustness by default
but the option to choose sort of how
much robustness whether it's one node
robust or whether that's popeater to
multiple nodes before we consider it
safe or the other way which is to
increase the performance at the expense
of robustness it's interesting and that
sounds like it's something that's been
actively developed at the moment are
there any other features that we should
look forward to coming in in the near
future well I think there's there's a
couple of things that are really worth
mentioning along the way that people
don't always understand I think in the
early days of relational databases when
you wanted to do something like add a
column to a table it would lock the
whole table for like an hour while you
added the column yeah
and that was one of the reasons why the
no sequel guys gonna said oh no don't do
that you just want a JSON blob and you
can do anything you want there and you
never need to do schemer upgrades and
that were at that time that was a sense
of
thought well what we've done in the
interim is we spent a long time
minimizing the lock levels that you need
on on your DDL commands and as a result
there were very few cases now where we
lock the whole table you can add indexes
concurrently you can add columns in just
a single metadata operation that takes
no time at all so there's a lot of
flexibility now built into two post
grades using experience running as a you
know 24/7 operational system so it's not
the type of thing where people say you
know you'd better take the database down
at 5 p.m. and and do that now you know
we almost all of our systems are running
24/7 you know even on Christmas Day
right and what I would say is that in
the rush up to Christmas you'd probably
be amazed exactly what percentage of the
world's transactions actually run
through a Postgres database as part of
the the primary payment cycle so when
you're buying something for your loved
ones this Christmas just think about how
many of those transactions are running
through postcards and it's quite a
surprising number so it we're talking
hundreds of billions of dollars annually
flow through postcode databases because
the financial services industry trusts
it Wow okay I think on that no that's
that's that could be a good place to
finish where can work on our listeners
go to find out more about house grocer
and the features that we've been talking
about today
well PostgreSQL de org is the website to
visit or if you look up Postgres you'll
find pages on the open source project
and all of the commercial companies
around it that come to conferences
that's a great place to discuss your
data needs these users giving
presentations there's people listening
to things and people chatting about
their what they need of all these
technologies so
it's always good to come and join in the
community well Simon thank you very much
for coming on the show and the software
engineering radio this is Simon crossly
thank you for listening thank you very
much thanks for listening the SU radio
an educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening